Register of the Pathfinder Press Publications, 1922-2014
Hoover Institution Archives
Pathfinder Press Publications
1922-2014
92116
Hoover Institution Archives
52 manuscript boxes, 5 phonotape cassettes, 1 envelope (21.8 linear feet)
Record copies of books, pamphlets, and bulletins, relating to Marxist theory and socialist political analysis and commentary, and including works of Leon Trotsky, Fidel Castro, Malcolm X and others. Includes publications of Pioneer Publishers, Merit Publishers, and Monad Press, predecessors of Pathfinder Press; publications issued directly by the Socialist Workers Party and affiliates; and foreign-language translations of Pathfinder Press publications. Also includes some unpublished material related to publishing projects.
Pathfinder Press.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired a large collection of record copies of publications by Pathfinder Press, its predecessors and related publishing houses in 1992. A register to the Pathfinder Press Publications Collection was prepared in 1994 and remains the principal overall description of and finding aid to the collection. Since its preparation additional shipments of material have been received and described in this register.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Pathfinder Press descends from Pioneer Publishers, a publishing house established in New York City in 1930 in affiliation with the Communist League of America (predecessor of the Socialist Workers Party). Pioneer Publishers was superseded by Merit Publishers in 1965, and Merit Publishers in turn was superseded by Pathfinder Press in 1969. Monad Press, which operated between 1972 and 1986, was closely associated with Pathfinder Press.
Pathfinder Press and its predecessors have been publishers of works of Marxist theory and of socialist political analysis and commentary. They have been the principal English-language publishers of writings of Leon Trotsky, and have also been publishers of documentary works on the history of the early years of the Communist International, and on the histories of the Fourth International and the Socialist Workers Party; writings of James P. Cannon and other Socialist Workers Party leaders; and writings of such international figures as Malcolm X, Fidel Castro, Ernesto Guevara, the Sandinista leaders, Maurice Bishop, Thomas Sankara, and Nelson Mandela.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection of record copies of books, pamphlets and bulletins published by Pathfinder Press and its predecessors was assembled and maintained by Pathfinder Press in New York City until its deposit in the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992. Pathfinder Press descends from Pioneer Publishers, a publishing house established in New York City in 1930 in affiliation with the Communist League of America (predecessor of the Socialist Workers Party). Pioneer Publishers was superseded by Merit Publishers in 1965, and Merit Publishers in turn was superseded by Pathfinder Press in 1969. Monad Press, which operated between 1972 and 1986, was closely associated with Pathfinder Press.
The collection includes a virtually complete set of all Pioneer, Merit, Monad and Pathfinder titles ever published. There is a distinct series of Education for Socialists bulletins. The collection also includes a number of related publications distributed by Pathfinder Press but appearing under other imprints. These consist principally of pamphlets and other works published directly by the Socialist Workers Party, its predecessors and affiliates, and associated election campaign and legal defense organizations; and foreign-language translations of works published originally by Pathfinder Press and its predecessors. Other copies of books in the collection will be found in the Hoover Institution Library and Stanford University Library.
A small volume of unpublished material, including a typescript for a book, and background research material assembled in preparation of books, also forms part of the collection.
Scope and Content of the Incremental Materials
The incremental materials consist primarily of publications dated 1993 and after. However there are a few earlier items. In addition there is a small volume of working material used by Pathfinder Press in preparation of three volumes relating to the early history of the Communist International and of the Soviet Communist Party.
A second set of incremental materials includes a large number of Persian-language imprints of Pathfinder titles published in association with Iranian publishers. Also included is an unpublished documentary manuscript on the case of Aníbal Escalante in Cuba.
Castro, Fidel, 1926-; Fourth International.; Merit Publishers.; Monad Press.; Pioneer Publishers.; Socialist Workers Party.; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965.; Audiotapes.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Publishers and publishing--United States.; Socialism--United States.; Socialism.; United States--Politics and government.
- UNPUBLISHED MATERIAL, 1988-1993 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Typescript for a book, and background material accumulated in preparation of books. Arranged by physical form.
  - Background material for publication projects (Box 1)
    - Babaie, Dr. Memorandum by Samad Yerevani, 1993, re conversations with Dr. Babaie, Azerbaijaini revolutionary, concerning his memories of the Congress of the Peoples of the East, Baku, 1920. Used in preparation of Congress of the Peoples of the East (1920: Baku, Azerbaijan), To See the Dawn (Pathfinder Press, q.v.)
    - Bjarnason, Brynjolfur. Memoranda by Otto Masson, 1988-1989, summarizing interviews with Brynjolfur Bjarnason, Icelandic communist, concerning his memories of the 2nd World Congress of the Communist International, 1920, and related printed matter. Used in preparation of Communist International. Congress (2nd: 1920: Petrograd, Russia), Workers of the World and Oppressed Peoples, Unite! (Pathfinder Press, q.v.), 1991
    - Shipman, Charles. Transcript of interview of Charles Shipman, Mexican-American communist, conducted by Robert Dees, 1988, concerning Shipman's memories of the 2nd World Congress of the Communist International, 1920. Used in preparation of Communist International. Congress (2nd: 1920: Petrograd, Russia), Workers of the World and Oppressed Peoples, Unite! (Pathfinder Press, q.v.). See also SOUND RECORDINGS and PHOTOGRAPHS, 1991
  - Typescript. Trotsky, Leon. "The War Correspondence of Leon Trotsky: World War I, " Translated and prepared by Brian Pearce. 1992. 3 volumes, 1914-1917.
- PIONEER PUBLISHERS IMPRINTS, 1931-1965. (Box 1-4)
  Books and pamphlets published by Pioneer Publishers. All items published in New York City unless otherwise specified. Arranged chronologically.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Permanent Revolution. 157 p. Cf. Merit (1969), Pathfinder (1986) and Related Foreign (Spain) imprints, 1931. (Box 1)
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Spanish Revolution in Danger! 62 p., 1931.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Germany: The Key to the International Situation. 45 p., 1932.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Problems of the Chinese Revolution. 432 p., 1932.
  - Trotsky, Leon. What Next? Vital Questions for the German Proletariat. 192 p., 1932. (Box 2)
  - Reese, Maria. I Accuse Stalinism! An Open Letter to the C.C. of the Communist Party of Germany and the E.C.C.I. 16 p., 1933.
  - Shachtman, Max. Ten Years: History and Principles of the Left Opposition. 79 p., 1933.
  - Swabeck, Arne. Unemployment and the American Working Class. 23 p., 1933.
  - Trotsky, Leon. In Defense of the Russian Revolution. 45 p., 1933.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Only Road. 93 p. Cf. Related Foreign (Sri Lanka) imprint, 1933.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Soviet Economy in Danger: The Expulsion of Zinoviev. 67 p., 1933.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Soviet Union and the Fourth International: The Class Nature of the Soviet State. 31 p. Cf. Related Foreign (Sri Lanka) imprint, 1934.
  - Trotsky, Leon. War and the Fourth International: Draft Theses. Adopted by the International Secretariat of the International Communist League. 35 p., 1934.
  - Muste, A. J. Which Party for the American Worker? 31 p., 1935.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Kirov Assassination. 32 p., 1935.
  - ----------. Leon Trotsky on the Kirov Assassination. Reprint. 32 p., 1956.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Suppressed Testament of Lenin: The Complete Original Text with Two Explanatory Articles. 47 p., 1935.
  - ----------. Reprint. 48 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1946.
  - Morrow, Felix. The Civil War in Spain. 64 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1936.
  - Shachtman, Max. Behind the Moscow Trial. 142 p., 1936.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Third International after Lenin. 357 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1936.
  - World Voices on the Moscow Trials: A Compilation from the Labor and Liberal Press of the World. 64 p., 1936.
  - Adler, Friedrich. The Witchcraft Trial in Moscow. 32 p., 1937.
  - Burnham, James. The People's Front: The New Betrayal. 64 p., 1937.
  - James, C. L. R. World Revolution, 1917-1936: The Rise and Fall of the Communist International. 429 p., 1937.
  - Trotsky, Leon. I Stake My Life! 24 p. Cf. Related Foreign (Mexico) imprint, 1937.
  - Trotsky, Leon. In Defense of the Soviet Union. 40 p., 1937.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Lessons of October. 125 p., 1937.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Stalin School of Falsification. 326 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1937.
  - Why Did They "Confess"? A Study of the Radek-Piatakov Trial. 30 p., 1937.
  - Goldman, Albert. What Is Socialism? Three Lectures for Workers. 47 p., 1938. (Box 3)
  - Macdonald, Dwight. Fascism and the American Scene. 29 p., 1938.
  - Burnham, James. Let the People Vote on War! p., 1939? 14
  - Hansen, Joseph. Father Coughlin: Fascist Demagogue. 30 p., 1939.
  - ----------. 2nd edition. 30 p., 1939.
  - James, C. L. R. Why Negroes Should Oppose the War. By J. R. Johnson [pseudonym] p., 1939? 31
  - Breitman, George. Defend the Negro Sailors of the U.S.S. Philadelphia. By Albert Parker [pseudonym] 15 p., 1940.
  - Cannon, James P. To the Memory of the Old Man: Leon Trotsky Memorial Address. 15 p., 1940.
  - Goldman, Albert. The Assassination of Leon Trotsky: The Proofs of Stalin's Guilt. 74 p. Cf. Related Foreign (Mexico) imprint, 1940.
  - Goldman, Albert. Why We Defend the Soviet Union. 31 p., 1940.
  - Hansen, Joseph. Wall Street's War, Not Ours! 16 p., 1940.
  - Breitman, George. Negroes March on Washington. By Albert Parker [pseudonym] 15 p., 1941.
  - Morrow, Felix. Labor's Answer to Conscription. 15 p., 1941.
  - Teachers and the War. 23 p., 1941.
  - Today's Fight against the Bosses. p., 1941? 7
  - Varlin, Eugene. The Negro and the U.S. Army. 29 p., 1941.
  - Breitman, George. The March on Washington One Year After. By Albert Parker [pseudonym] 15 p., 1942.
  - Cannon, James P. Socialism on Trial: The Official Court Record of James P. Cannon's Testimony in the Famous Minneapolis "Sedition" Trial. 116 p., 1942.
  - ----------. 2nd edition. 111 p., 1944.
  - ----------. 3rd edition. 111 p., 1949.
  - ----------. 4th edition. 1965. 111 p. Cf. Merit (1969), Pathfinder and Related Foreign (Iran) imprints, (1973, 1981)
  - Cannon, James P. The Workers and the Second World War. 46 p., 1942.
  - Trotsky, Leon. In Defense of Marxism: Against the Petty-Bourgeois Opposition. 211 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1973) and Related Foreign (Spain) imprints, 1942.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Their Morals and Ours. 48 p., 1942.
  - ----------. Mexico City, p. Cf. Merit (1966), Pathfinder (1972) and Related Foreign (Spain) imprints, 1942? 64
  - Breitman, George. Negroes in the Post-War World. By Albert Parker [pseudonym] 15 p., 1943.
  - Breitman, George. Wartime Crimes of Big Business. 15 p., 1943.
  - Burch, Arthur. The Struggle for Negro Equality. By John Saunders [pseudonym] and Albert Parker [pseudonym of George Breitman] 2nd enlarged edition. 47 p., 1943.
  - ----------. 3rd edition. 47 p., 1945.
  - Cannon, James P. The End of the Comintern. Bound with Fourth International, The Manifesto of the Fourth International. 35 p., 1943.
  - Curtiss, Charles. Your Standard of Living: What's Happening to It? By. C. Charles [pseudonym] 2nd revised edition. 30 p., 1943.
  - Lovell, Frank. Maritime: A Historical Sketch and a Workers' Program. By Frederick J. Lang [pseudonym] 171 p., 1943.
  - Cannon, James P. The Russian Revolution. 30 p., 1944.
  - Goldman, Albert. In Defense of Socialism: The Official Court Record of Albert Goldman's Final Speech for the Defense in the Famous Minneapolis "Sedition" Trial. 92 p., 1944.
  - Hansen, Joseph. American Workers Need a Labor Party. 44 p., 1944.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Fascism: What It Is, How to Fight It. 47 p., 1944.
  - ----------. Reprint. 43 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1962.
  - Why We Are in Prison: Farewell Speeches of the Eighteen SWP and 544-CIO Minneapolis Prisoners. 55 p., 1944.
  - Keemer, Edgar. A Practical Program to Kill Jim Crow. By Charles Jackson [pseudonym] 15 p., 1945.
  - ----------. 2nd enlarged edition. 23 p., 1945.
  - Preis, Art. Jobs for All! A Fighting Program for Labor. 23 p., 1945.
  - Socialist Workers Party. The United States and the Second World War. Bound with Socialist Workers Party, The European Revolution and Tasks of the Revolutionary Party. 46 p., 1945.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Revolution Betrayed: What Is the Soviet Union and Where Is It Going? 1945. 308 p. Cf. Pathfinder and Related Foreign (Spain) imprints, (1972, 1992)
  - Trotsky, Leon. The First Five Years of the Communist International. 2 volumes. Cf. Monad (1972) imprint, 1945-1953. (Box 4)
  - Carsten, Charles. Veterans and Labor: A Program of Action. 23 p., 1946.
  - Clarke, George. Build a Labor Party Now. 15 p., 1946.
  - Fourth International. Only Victorious Socialist Revolutions Can Prevent the Third World War! 31 p., 1946.
  - Trotsky, Leon. The Death Agony of Capitalism and the Tasks of the Fourth International: The Transitional Program. Adopted by the Founding Conference of the Fourth International. 64 p., 1946.
  - ----------. Reprint. 1964. 64 p. Cf. Pathfinder and Related Foreign (Argentina, Japan, Spain) imprints, (1970, 1973)
  - Cannon, James P. American Stalinism and Anti-Stalinism. 48 p., 1947.
  - Cannon, James P. The Coming American Revolution. 31 p., 1947.
  - Preis, Art. Stalinists on the Waterfront. 31 p., 1947.
  - Socialist Workers Party. National Committee. Fight the Slave Labor Law! 15 p., 1947.
  - Bohannan, William E. A Letter to American Negroes. 15 p., 1948.
  - Hansen, Joseph. The Socialist Workers Party: What It Is, What It Stands For. 30 p., 1948.
  - ----------. Revised edition. 54 p., 1958.
  - The Voice of Socialism: Radio Speeches by the Socialist Workers Party Candidates in the 1948 Election. 31 p.
  - Preis, Art. "Welfare State" or Socialism? 36 p., 1950.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Stalin's Frame-up System and the Moscow Trials. 144 p., 1950.
  - Cannon, James P. The Road to Peace: According to Stalin and According to Lenin. 48 p., 1951.
  - Breitman, George. Jim Crow Murder of Mr. and Mrs. Harry T. Moore. 31 p., 1952.
  - Cannon, James P. America's Road to Socialism. 79 p. Includes two variant printings. Cf. Pathfinder (1975) imprint, 1953.
  - McCarthyism: American Fascism on the March. 16 p., 1953.
  - Mayhew, Howard. Racial Terror at Trumbull Park, Chicago. 15 p., 1954.
  - Stop McCarthyism! Your Stake in the Fight. 16 p., 1954.
  - Simon, Jean. Desegregation! Labor's Stake in the Fight for Negro Equality. 16 p., 1955.
  - Cannon, James P. The Debs Centennial. 40 p. Cf. Merit (1967) imprint, 1956.
  - Cannon, James P. The I.W.W.: On the Fiftieth Anniversary of the Founding Convention. 44 p. Cf. Merit (1967) imprint, 1956.
  - Banda, Michael. The Chinese Communist Party and the Hungarian Revolution. 22 p., 1957.
  - Cowley, Joyce. The Santana Case: Tragedy of a Puerto Rican Youth. 17 p., 1957.
  - Regroupment: A Programmatic Basis for Discussion of Socialist Unity. 8 p., 1957.
  - Socialist Workers Party. The Class-Struggle Road to Negro Equality. 23 p., 1957.
  - Socialist Workers Party. National Committee. Revolution in Hungary and the Crisis of Stalinism. 34 p., 1957.
  - Trotsky, Leon. If America Should Go Communist. 21 p., 1957.
  - Cannon, James P. Socialist Election Policy in 1958. 11 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1968) imprint
  - Cannon, James P. Socialism and Democracy. 21 p., 1959.
  - Breitman, George. Anti-Negro Prejudice: When It Began, When It Will End. 11 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1971) imprint, 1960.
  - Hansen, Joseph. Too Many Babies? 48 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1960.
  - Novack, George. The Long View of History. By William F. Warde [pseudonym] 64 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1979) imprint, 1960.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Stalinism and Bolshevism: Concerning the Historical and Theoretical Roots of the Fourth International. 2nd printing. 27 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1960.
  - Halstead, Fred. Why Can't Everybody Have a Job? 15 p., 1961.
  - Hansen, Joseph. In Defense of the Cuban Revolution: An Answer to the State Department and Theodore Draper. 30 p., 1961.
  - Ring, Harry. How Cuba Uprooted Race Discrimination. 15 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1972) imprints, 1961.
  - Castro, Fidel. Fidel Castro Denounces Bureaucracy and Sectarianism. 40 p., 1962.
  - Castro, Fidel. The Revolution Must Be a School of Unfettered Thought. 14 p., 1962.
  - Castro, Fidel. The Second Declaration of Havana. 23 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1984) imprint, 1962.
  - Castro, Fidel. The Road to Revolution in Latin America. 32 p., 1963.
  - Kerry, Tom. Labor Party and Freedom Now Party: An Answer to the New York Times. 11 p., 1963.
  - Novack, George. An Introduction to the Logic of Marxism. By William F. Warde [pseudonym] 3rd revised edition. 107 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1942), Merit (1966), Pathfinder (1971) and Related Foreign (Argentina, Greece, Mexico, Spain) imprints, 1963.
  - Novack, George. Moscow vs. Peking: The Meaning of the Great Debate. 30 p., 1963.
  - Socialist Workers Party. Freedom Now: New Stage in the Struggle for Negro Emancipation. 23 p., 1963.
  - Cruse, Harold. Marxism and the Negro Struggle. By Harold Cruse, George Breitman and Clifton DeBerry. 48 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1965.
  - Fourth International. United Secretariat. Khrushchev's Downfall. Bound with Joseph Hansen, New Deepening of the Sino-Soviet Rift? 15 p., 1965.
  - Novack, George. Uneven and Combined Development in History. By William F. Warde [pseudonym] 59 p. Cf. Merit (1966) and Related Foreign (Colombia, Portugal) imprints, 1965.
  - Vernon, Robert. Watts and Harlem: The Rising Revolt in the Black Ghettos. By Robert Vernon and George Novack. 15 p., 1965.
- MERIT PUBLISHERS IMPRINTS, 1965-1969. (Box 4-6)
  Books and pamphlets published by Merit Publishers. All items published in New York City. Arranged chronologically.
  - X, Malcolm. Malcolm X Speaks: Selected Speeches and Statements. Edited by George Breitman. 1965. 242 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1966), Pathfinder and Related Foreign (France, Italy, Japan, Sweden) imprints, (1984, 1989, 1993) (Box 4)
  - The Black Panther Party. 29 p., 1966.
  - Breitman, George. How a Minority Can Change Society. 2nd edition. 24 p., 1966.
  - ----------. 4th printing. 30 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1964) and Pathfinder (1971) imprints, 1969.
  - The Catastrophe in Indonesia: Three Articles on the Fatal Consequences of Communist Party Policy. 47 p., 1966.
  - Marxist Essays in American History. 128 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1976) imprint, 1966. (Box 5)
  - Novack, George. An Introduction to the Logic of Marxism. 4th revised edition. 124 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1942), Pioneer (1963), Pathfinder (1971) and Related Foreign (Argentina, Greece, Mexico, Spain) imprints, 1966.
  - Novack, George. Uneven and Combined Development in History. 3rd edition. 59 p. First published by Pioneer Publishers (1965, q.v.) Cf. Related Foreign (Colombia, Portugal) imprints, 1966.
  - Rossa, Della. Why Watts Exploded: How the Ghetto Fought Back. 21 p., 1966.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Their Morals and Ours: Marxist versus Liberal Views on Morality: Four Essays. By Leon Trotsky, John Dewey and George Novack. 78 p. Revision of Pioneer Publishers edition (1942, q.v.) Cf. Pathfinder (1972) and Related Foreign (Spain) imprints, 1966.
  - Behind China's "Great Cultural Revolution". By Peng Shu-tse et al. 63 p., 1967.
  - The Black Uprisings: Newark, Detroit, 1967. 30 p.
  - Cannon, James P. E. V. Debs: The Socialist Movement of His Time, Its Meaning for Today. 2nd edition of The Debs Centennial. 30 p. First published by Pioneer Publishers (1956, q.v.), 1967.
  - Cannon, James P. The I.W.W. 2nd edition. 31 p. First published by Pioneer Publishers (1956, q.v.), 1967.
  - Castro, Fidel. Fidel Castro's Tribute to Che Guevara. 14 p., 1967.
  - Deutscher, Isaac. On Socialist Man. 29 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1986) imprint, 1967.
  - Guevara, Ernesto. Che Guevara on Vietnam and World Revolution. 15 p., 1967.
  - Novack, George. The Understanding of History: Two Essays. 39 p., 1967.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Leon Trotsky on Black Nationalism and Self-Determination. 66 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1967.
  - X, Malcolm. Malcolm X on Afro-American History. 48 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) and Related Foreign (Netherlands) imprints, 1967.
  - Browne, Robert S. Should the U.S. Be Partitioned into Two Separate and Independent Nations, One a Homeland for White Americans and the Other a Homeland for Black Americans? A Symposium. By Robert S. Browne and Robert Vernon. 30 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1968.
  - Castro, Fidel. A New Stage in the Advance of Cuban Socialism. 48 p., 1968.
  - Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials. The Case of Leon Trotsky: Report of Hearings. 617 p., 1968.
  - Frank, Pierre. The Worker-Student Uprising of 1968: First Phase of the French Socialist Revolution. 48 p.
  - Murder in Memphis: Martin Luther King and the Future of the Black Liberation Struggle. By Paul Boutelle et al. 15 p., 1968.
  - Trotsky, Leon. Whither France? 160 p. Reprint of Pioneer Publishers edition, 1968.
  - Antiwar GIs Speak Out: Interviews with Fort Jackson GIs United against the War. By Fred Halstead. 47 p., 1969.
  - Buch, Peter. Burning Issues of the Mideast Crisis. 29 p. Cf. Related Foreign (Argentina) imprint, 1969.
  - Cannon, James P. Socialism on Trial: The Official Court Record of James P. Cannon's Testimony in the Famous Minneapolis "Sedition" Trial. 1969. 111 p. Reprint of Pioneer Publishers edition (1942, q.v.) Cf. Pathfinder and Related Foreign (Iran) imprints, (1973, 1981)
  - Cowley, Joyce. Pioneers of Women's Liberation. 15 p., 1969.
  - Hansen, Beatrice. A Political Biography of Walter Reuther: The Record of an Opportunist. 23 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1987) imprint, 1969.
  - Industrial Workers of the World. The Founding Convention of the IWW: Proceedings. 616 p., 1969.
  - The Invasion of Czechoslovakia. 47 p., 1969. (Box 6)
  - Mandel, Ernest. The Marxist Theory of the State. 31 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1971) imprint, 1969.
  - Mandel, Ernest. On the Revolutionary Potential of the Working Class. By Ernest Mandel and George Novack. 46 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1969.